<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ddd | Matthieu Napoli]]></title>
  <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/categories/ddd/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-30T09:17:53+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mnapoli.fr/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthieu Napoli]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Repository interface]]></title>
    <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/repository-interface/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T18:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mnapoli.fr/repository-interface</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here is the definition of a repository for Eric Evans in his
<a href="http://books.google.fr/books/about/Domain_driven_Design.html?id=7dlaMs0SECsC&amp;redir_esc=y">Domain Driven Design</a> book:</p>

<blockquote><p>A <em>repository</em> represents all objects of a certain type as a conceptual set (usually emulated).
<strong>It acts like a collection</strong>, except with more elaborate querying capability.
[&hellip;]
For each type of object that needs global access, <strong>create an object that can provide the illusion
of an in-memory collection</strong> of all objects of that type.</p></blockquote>

<p>While I love Doctrine, I really dislike
<a href="https://github.com/doctrine/common/blob/master/lib/Doctrine/Common/Persistence/ObjectRepository.php">their repository interface</a>
because it doesn&rsquo;t look and act like a collection.
And that&rsquo;s too bad because Doctrine even provides a very good abstraction for collections
through the <code>doctrine/collection</code> project. It even supports filtering with criterias over collections <strong>and</strong> repositories.</p>

<p>I know that Doctrine is not targeted at Domain Driven Design only, but I think having a better repository interface
would still benefit the project and the users.</p>

<p>Here is a basic repository interface I tend to use instead:</p>

<p>```php
interface Repository
{</p>

<pre><code>function add($entity);

function remove($entity);

function count();

/**
 * @throws NotFoundException
 * @return object
 */
function get($id);

/**
 * @return array
 */
function find(Criteria $criteria);

function toArray();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Of course, you should use this interface as a base and write your own repository interfaces for each aggregate root.</p>

<h2>Collection verbs</h2>

<p>Why use verbs like<code>add</code> and <code>remove</code> instead of <code>load</code>, <code>save</code>, <code>delete</code>, <code>persist</code>, …?</p>

<p>Because those are persistence-related terms and have nothing to do in an interface
that is going to be used/extended in the domain layer.</p>

<h2>Get versus Find</h2>

<p>I really dislike that you can only <code>find</code> in Doctrine: it will return null if no entity is found.</p>

<p>Most of the time, that is not what you want. You actually don&rsquo;t want to &ldquo;search and find&rdquo; the entity,
you just want to get it by its id and you assume it exists.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s why you need to clearly differentiate between find and get:</p>

<ul>
<li>method starting with <code>get</code> should always return an entity, or throw an exception if not found</li>
<li>method starting with <code>find</code> should always return a collection (that could be empty)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Going further: the collection interface</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve said it already, but a repository should behave like a collection.
The interface shown above is not completely satisfying yet because it doesn&rsquo;t totally behave like a collection.
For example you can&rsquo;t iterate it.</p>

<p>So the best solution is simple: <strong>write a sensible collection interface and have the repository extend it</strong>.</p>

<p>```php
interface Collection extends Countable, IteratorAggregate, ArrayAccess
{</p>

<pre><code>function add($element);

function remove($element);

function clear();

function contains($element);

function get($key);

function find(Criteria $criteria);

function toArray();

function slice($offset, $length = null);
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>interface Repository extends Collection
{
}
```</p>

<p>(this is a very simple version, not exhaustive at all)</p>

<p>Now this is much better.
<strong>You can even type-hint against the collection and accept at the same time collections and repositories!</strong></p>

<p>You can then iterate or filter the collection without having to care what the object really is.
For example, you can write a <code>ProductCriteria</code> and use it both on the repository and collections of products.</p>

<p>Example: let&rsquo;s say you write a controller to display a product list:</p>

<p>```php
class ProductListController
{</p>

<pre><code>/**
 * @var ProductCollection
 */
private $products;

public function __construct(ProductCollection $products)
{
    $this-&gt;products = $products;
}

public function listAction()
{
    return new View('product-list.twig.html', [$this-&gt;products]);
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Here your controller is completely reusable. If you give it the <code>ProductRepository</code>, it can display the whole
product list. If you give it the list of favorite products of the user, it will work too.
Thank you dependency injection!</p>

<p>And the day PHP gets generics, that will be even nicer (<code>Collection&lt;Product&gt;</code>) but that&rsquo;s a debate for another day!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Friend services?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/friend-services/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-09T17:03:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mnapoli.fr/friend-services</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Using the Domain Driven Design methodology, I sometimes end up on such a situation: a behavior in a model class is complex and involving other classes. It’s time to put that behavior in a service (or a factory if the situation applies to a constructor).</p>

<p>The problem is that in my service, I am not in the context of the domain class. If I move <code>Foo::something()</code> into <code>FooService::something($foo)</code>, then <strong>I can’t access private properties of Foo</strong>, thus limiting me to the public API of Foo.</p>

<p>Now I end up adding accessors, thus breaking encapsulation and complexifying everything where all I wanted was improving the code.</p>

<p>VB.Net has a concept of “Friend” visibility, i.e. if A is friend with B, then A can access private properties of B (or something like that it’s been a long time :p). PHP doesn’t have such a concept natively, but here is a tryout to apply it with workarounds.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><em>Disclaimer</em>: the code is not pretty and is not for production. This is just an idea thrown around.</p>

<p>```php
&lt;?php
class Foo {</p>

<pre><code>private $bar = 'hello world';
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>class FriendOfFoo {</p>

<pre><code>public function doSomething($foo) {
    return function() use ($foo) {
        echo $foo-&gt;bar;
    };
}
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>$foo = new Foo();</p>

<p>$service = new FriendOfFoo();</p>

<p>$closure = $service->doSomething($foo)&ndash;>bindTo(null, $foo);</p>

<p>$closure();
```</p>

<p>See it in action on <a href="http://3v4l.org/e9RNO">3v4l.org</a>.</p>

<p>Here, FriendOfFoo is a service that has access to Foo’s private and protected properties.</p>

<p>We achieve that by writing the methods of the service into closures. We can then <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/closure.bindto.php">bind those closures to the context of Foo</a>, and voilà!</p>

<p>If you see a better way of achieving this, I am interested.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
