<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: architecture | Matthieu Napoli]]></title>
  <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/categories/architecture/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-21T15:10:58+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mnapoli.fr/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthieu Napoli]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Decoupling packages]]></title>
    <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/decoupling-packages/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-21T23:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mnapoli.fr/decoupling-packages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Decoupling packages is a hard thing. There are not a lot of options, and this blog post is about how some options are better than others.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say for example that you are writing a &ldquo;package&rdquo;, or library, to respond to HTTP requests (that kind of package could be considered the basis for a web framework). How do you handle routing?</p>

<p>If you write your Router package as an independent package (which is good: small and specialized packages are more reusable and maintainable), you might not want to couple the HTTP package to the Router package: you want to leave users free to choose the router of their choice.</p>

<p>So, what are your options to make the HTTP package and the Router package decoupled from each other?</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Events</h2>

<p>The first option is to turn to <strong>event-driven programming</strong>. By relying on an &ldquo;event manager&rdquo; library/package, you can have your package raise specific events at strategic points in your code. And you can have those events affect the code flow.</p>

<p>This is the solution chosen by Symfony to solve the routing problem exposed earlier. Their HttpKernel component is decoupled form their Routing component through events.</p>

<p>Here is the simplified code flow of their <code>HttpKernel</code> class/component (which is the basis for an HTTP application):</p>

<p>```php
$eventDispatcher->dispatch(</p>

<pre><code>KernelEvents::REQUEST,
new GetResponseEvent($this, $request, $type)
</code></pre>

<p>);</p>

<p>$controller = $request->attributes->get(&lsquo;_controller&rsquo;);</p>

<p>if (! $controller) {</p>

<pre><code>throw new NotFoundHttpException();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>So here is what&rsquo;s happening:</p>

<ul>
<li>the <code>HttpKernel</code> raises a &ldquo;Kernel Request&rdquo; event</li>
<li>then <strong>it expects</strong> that a listener set the controller under the &ldquo;_controller&rdquo; key in the request</li>
</ul>


<p>So is <code>HttpKernel</code> decoupled from the <code>Router</code> component? <strong>Yes</strong>. The listener that sets the controller could actually be anything.</p>

<p>The problem is, as emphasized above, that the <code>HttpKernel</code> <strong>expects something very specific from the listeners</strong>. The whole application depends on an unknown listener being actually registered for that particular event and following an exact, <strong>unspecified</strong> behavior.</p>

<p>I believe events should be used for hooking up in the main logic flow to <em>extend it</em>. <strong>But the main logic flow should be linear and not rely on the possible <em>side effects</em> of an event.</strong></p>

<p>There are some other problems we can find with this solution:</p>

<ul>
<li>the package ends up coupled to the &ldquo;event manager&rdquo; package (you just replaced a dependency by another)</li>
<li>the code is not linear: it makes it much harder for developers to put the pieces back together and contribute to the project</li>
<li>behavior from decoupled packages <strong>are not specified by contracts</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Regarding the pros:</p>

<ul>
<li>the behavior is <em>not specified</em>, which can also be a good thing: it leaves every possible option open for the future</li>
<li>might be simpler than the other options</li>
</ul>


<p><code>&lt;disclaimer&gt;</code>Just to be clear, Symfony is an exceptional framework and I love it. I am sure the decision to choose this option was carefully thought through, and the important thing to remember is that <strong>it works</strong>. Symfony is probably the most popular modern PHP framework, and my blog post doesn&rsquo;t change that. I am just using it as an example here, I just want to expose alternative options and discuss the pros and cons.<code>&lt;/disclaimer&gt;</code></p>

<h2>Interfaces and adapters</h2>

<p>I was mentioning <em>specifying behaviors</em> with <strong>contracts</strong>. In PHP (and most OO languages), you can implement this using <strong>interfaces</strong>.</p>

<p>If we take the previous example, an HTTP package could contain a <code>RouterInterface</code> to specify how a routing component should behave (this is a very basic example):</p>

<p>```php
namespace Acme\Http;</p>

<p>interface RouterInterface {</p>

<pre><code>/**
 * @return callable The controller to use for this request
 */
public function route(Request $request);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll notice that not everything is specifiable, e.g. the return types. Hopefully PHP will allow that in its next major version, but until then the only solution is to use documentation.</p>

<p>In the <code>HttpApplication</code> class, we can use it in type-hints to accept any implementation (classic dependency injection here). And here is what the code logic would look like:</p>

<p>```php
$controller = $router->route($request);</p>

<p>if (! $controller) {</p>

<pre><code>throw new NotFoundHttpException();
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p><strong>The code flow is linear and completely explicit.</strong> And the HTTP package is decoupled from any Router package!</p>

<p>The only problem left: Router packages would be forced to implement <code>Acme\Http\RouterInterface</code> if they want to be used with the HTTP package. Because of that, they end up coupled to it… So how do we decouple Router packages from the HTTP package?</p>

<p>A way to go around that is to use <strong>adapters</strong>:</p>

<p>```php
namespace \MyApplication\Adapter;</p>

<p>class HttpRouterInterfaceAdapter implements \Acme\Http\RouterInterface {</p>

<pre><code>private $router;

public function __construct(\Acme\Router\Router $router) {
    $this-&gt;router = $router;
}

public function route(Request $request) {
      $this-&gt;router-&gt;route($request);
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Thanks to that adapter, the <code>Router</code> class doesn&rsquo;t need to implement the <code>RouterInterface</code>. So it is completely decoupled from the HTTP package.</p>

<p>However, as you can see, it requires writing an adapter each time you want to &ldquo;connect&rdquo; decoupled packages.</p>

<p>Pros:</p>

<ul>
<li>linear and explicit code flow</li>
<li>specified behavior (using interfaces)</li>
</ul>


<p>Cons:</p>

<ul>
<li>requires to write interfaces</li>
<li>requires to write adapters</li>
</ul>


<p>This strategy of interfaces was recently used by <strong>Laravel</strong>. For the version 5.0 (IIRC), Laravel will publish a package named <a href="https://github.com/illuminate/contracts"><code>illuminate/contracts</code></a> which contains all the interfaces used by its other packages.</p>

<p>That allows to have decoupled Laravel packages while not needing adapters to use them together: packages can implement the interfaces at the very small cost of being coupled to <code>illuminate/contracts</code> (it&rsquo;s a small cost because the package is very light and contains only interfaces).</p>

<h2>Standardized interfaces</h2>

<p>Now the last option is to go a step beyond and try to make the interfaces &ldquo;<strong>standard</strong>&rdquo;. By that I mean that the same interface would be used by many packages, and implemented by many others.</p>

<p>The good example for this is obviously <strong>logging</strong>. There used to be a numerous amount of different logger libraries for PHP. Then the <a href="http://www.php-fig.org/">PHP-FIG</a> group worked to produce <a href="https://github.com/php-fig/log">PSR-3</a>, the logger standard.</p>

<p>Today, many logging packages implement the <code>Psr\Log\LoggerInterface</code>, and most modern frameworks type-hint against that interface instead of specific implementations. That means that users can choose any PSR-3 compliant logger and have their framework use it.</p>

<p>Needless to say that this is an ideal situation: <strong>no coupling, no effort</strong>! But logging was kind of an easy topic. It&rsquo;s very hard to come up with standards for all the other components that need interfaces, mainly because implementations often differ a lot.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.php-fig.org/">PHP-FIG</a> has been working for a few years on a Cache and an HTTP message PSR, and hopefully they will be released sometime. In the meantime, the <a href="https://github.com/container-interop/container-interop">container-interop project</a> aims at providing interfaces to standardize the usage of dependency injection containers.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>OK, there&rsquo;s not much left to add here, if you have any reaction about this I&rsquo;d be happy to hear it. If I got anything wrong, I&rsquo;d be happy to correct it.</p>

<p>I would like to finish on an idea that was suggested about a year ago on the PHP internals mailing list: &ldquo;<strong>weak interfaces</strong>&rdquo;. Those are interfaces that define a behavior, but <strong>that do not need to be implemented by classes</strong>. It mixes the principle of static-typing with duck-typing:</p>

<blockquote><p>If it looks like a duck and quacks like a duck, then it&rsquo;s a duck.</p></blockquote>

<p>What&rsquo;s really good with this is that it allows packages to define their interfaces, and type-hint against it, all the while not requiring dependencies to actually implement it. As long as objects are compatible with the interface, it works. It&rsquo;s a sort of <code>class X implements Y</code> evaluated at runtime. Example:</p>

<p>```php
interface FooInterface {</p>

<pre><code>public function hello();
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>// Foo does not implement FooInterface
class Foo {</p>

<pre><code>// But this method makes it compatible with FooInterface
public function hello()
{
    return 'Hello world';
}
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>// That pseudo-syntax tells that this is a weak-interface type-hinting
function run(&lt;<FooInterface>> $foo) {</p>

<pre><code>echo $foo;
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>// It works because Foo is compatible with the interface
run(new Foo);</p>

<p>// Error, stdClass is not compatible with FooInterface
run(new stdClass);
```</p>

<p>This example was just for fun, but I wish such a feature would land in PHP (along with static return type). It would help a lot with package interoperability and decoupling.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> the original RFC about what I called <em>weak interfaces</em> has been linked to me by its author, Anthony Ferrara. Here it is: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/protocol_type_hinting">PHP RFC: Structural Type Hinting</a>. As you can see, it was named <em>Structural type hinting</em> instead of <em>weak interface</em>.</p>

<p>It has also been pointed to me in the comments that the same Anthony Ferrara wrote a userland implementation of this: <a href="https://github.com/ircmaxell/Protocol-Lib">ProtocolLib</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
