<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: silly | Matthieu Napoli]]></title>
  <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/categories/silly/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-30T09:18:45+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mnapoli.fr/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthieu Napoli]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Silly CLI 1.1 comes with dependency injection]]></title>
    <link href="http://mnapoli.fr/silly-cli/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-12T18:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mnapoli.fr/silly-cli</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have just released <a href="http://mnapoli.fr/silly/">Silly CLI</a> 1.1 and I think it&rsquo;s awesome, here&rsquo;s why.</p>

<h2>What is Silly?</h2>

<p>If you missed it, <a href="http://mnapoli.fr/silly/">Silly</a> is a small project I started a month ago. The idea is simple: <em>it is a CLI micro-framework</em>.</p>

<p>Much like Silex or Slim let you create a web application in a single file using closures as controllers, Silly let you create a CLI application in a single file using closures as commands:</p>

<p>```php
$app = new Silly\Application();</p>

<p>$app->command(&lsquo;greet [name] [&mdash;yell]&rsquo;, function ($name, $yell, $output) {</p>

<pre><code>$text = $name ? 'Hello '.$name : 'Hello';

if ($yell) {
    $text = strtoupper($text);
}

$output-&gt;writeln($text);
</code></pre>

<p>});</p>

<p>$app->run();
```</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As you can see, no need for classes. Also, commands are defined using a syntax inspired from help and man pages which is short and reads nicely.</p>

<p>Running the application:</p>

<p><code>
$ php app.php greet
Hello
$ php app.php greet john --yell
HELLO JOHN
</code></p>

<p>Of course I didn&rsquo;t reinvent anything. All this is based on <a href="http://symfony.com/fr/doc/current/components/console/introduction.html">Symfony Console</a>, which is great because:</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;m lazy</li>
<li>everybody knows the Symfony Console</li>
</ul>


<p>This was Silly CLI 1.0, and it was good.</p>

<h2>Scaling up</h2>

<p>I like micro-frameworks because they allow us to start very simply and very quickly. They also generally don&rsquo;t force us into a specific architecture or organization which, sometimes, is good.</p>

<p>But the value of a micro-framework is even greater when it allows you to <strong>scale up</strong>. By that I don&rsquo;t mean &ldquo;mongodb web-scale&rdquo;, I mean &ldquo;my single script file is too big, I want to organize everything more properly and start doing complex stuff&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Callables</h3>

<p>This is where a immensely useful concept of PHP comes into play: <strong>callables</strong>.</p>

<p>Most examples of micro-frameworks show you the &ldquo;closure&rdquo; example of callables because it&rsquo;s the most obvious one for a simple app:</p>

<p>```php
$app->command(&lsquo;greet [name]&rsquo;, function ($name) {</p>

<pre><code>// ...
</code></pre>

<p>});
```</p>

<p>But as you probably know, closures are not the only kind of <em>callables</em> in PHP. Here is a list of valid PHP callables:</p>

<ul>
<li>a closure: <code>function () {}</code></li>
<li>a function name: <code>'strlen'</code></li>
<li>an object method: <code>[$object, 'theMethod']</code></li>
<li>a class static method: <code>['TheClass', 'theMethod']</code></li>
<li>invokable object: <code>$object</code> (an object that has an <code>__invoke()</code> method)</li>
</ul>


<p>All that means is we can replace our closure with classes. Our simple example can then become:</p>

<p>```php
class GreetCommand
{</p>

<pre><code>public function execute($name)
{
    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>$app->command(&lsquo;greet [name]&rsquo;, [new GreetCommand, &lsquo;execute&rsquo;]);
```</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s a nice first step to organize our growing application. Each command can be put in its own class and file.</p>

<h2>Silly 1.1: Dependency injection</h2>

<p>Putting our commands in separate files is a good start. But everyone knows that a growing application is not just about organizing code: it&rsquo;s also about managing dependencies.</p>

<p>Instead of turning towards singletons or global functions/static methods, Silly 1.1 helps you into using dependency injection. More specifically, it comes with <strong>dependency injection container support</strong>.</p>

<h3>Choose your container</h3>

<p>Silex, Slim, Cilex, … all force you into using a specific container (often Pimple). While this is practical at first, it&rsquo;s usually not so good for <em>scaling up</em>: the more classes or dependencies you have, the more configuration you will write.</p>

<p>Instead of forcing you into using a <em>supposedly</em> better DI container, Silly goes <a href="https://github.com/container-interop/container-interop">the interoperability route</a>: <strong>use whichever container you want!</strong></p>

<p><code>php
$app-&gt;useContainer($container);
</code></p>

<p>The container you provide has to be compliant with the <a href="https://github.com/container-interop/container-interop">container-interop</a> standard. If it isn&rsquo;t you can use <a href="https://github.com/jeremeamia/acclimate-container">Acclimate</a>.</p>

<h3>Callables in the container</h3>

<p>By simply registering a container with <code>-&gt;useContainer()</code>, Silly will retrieve commands from the container when they are not PHP callables:</p>

<p>```php
// Valid PHP callables: doesn&rsquo;t use the container
$app->command(&lsquo;greet [name]&rsquo;, function () { /<em> &hellip; </em>/ });
$app->command(&lsquo;greet [name]&rsquo;, [new GreetCommand, &lsquo;execute&rsquo;]);
$app->command(&lsquo;greet [name]&rsquo;, [&lsquo;SomeClass&rsquo;, &lsquo;someStaticMethod&rsquo;]);
$app->command(&lsquo;greet [name]&rsquo;, new InvokableClassCommand);</p>

<p>// Use the container
$app->command(&lsquo;greet [name]&rsquo;, [&lsquo;GreetCommand&rsquo;, &lsquo;execute&rsquo;]); // execute is not a static method
$app->command(&lsquo;greet [name]&rsquo;, &lsquo;InvokableClassCommand&rsquo;);     // implements __invoke()
```</p>

<p>In the 2 last examples above, the container will be called to instantiate <code>GreetCommand</code> and <code>InvokableClassCommand</code>.</p>

<p>That means that you can configure those classes in your container and benefit from the dependency injection features of your container. For example:</p>

<p>```php
class GreetCommand
{</p>

<pre><code>private $entityManager;

public function __construct(EntityManager $entityManager)
{
    $this-&gt;entityManager = $entityManager;
}

public function execute($name)
{
    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Note that our class could also be an invokable class (i.e. one that <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/language.oop5.magic.php#object.invoke">implements <code>__invoke()</code></a>).</p>

<h3>Dependency injection in parameters</h3>

<p>Dependency injection as shown above only works when you write commands in classes. However you can&rsquo;t use it with closures!</p>

<p>To solve that problem, let&rsquo;s have a look at how dependency injection is performed in AngularJS:</p>

<p><code>js
angular.controller('MyController', function (myService, myOtherService) {
  // ...
});
</code></p>

<p>Silly supports the same mechanism of dependency injection through the callable parameters. For example:</p>

<p>```php
use Psr\Logger\LoggerInterface;</p>

<p>// the order of parameters doesn&rsquo;t matter:
$app->command(&lsquo;process [directory]&rsquo;, function (LoggerInterface $logger, $directory) {</p>

<pre><code>$logger-&gt;info('Processing directory ' . $directory);

// ...
</code></pre>

<p>});
```</p>

<p>Silly can inject services and values into parameters by looking into the container using:</p>

<ul>
<li>the <strong>type-hint</strong> (i.e. the interface/class name): <code>Psr\Logger\LoggerInterface</code></li>
<li>the <strong>parameter&rsquo;s name</strong>: <code>logger</code></li>
</ul>


<p>Depending on how you declare your container entries you might want to enable one or the other way, or both.</p>

<p><code>php
$app-&gt;useContainer($container, $injectByTypeHint = true, $injectByParameterName = true);
</code></p>

<p>If you set both to <code>true</code>, it will first look using the type-hint, then using the parameter name.</p>

<h2>The PHP-DI and Pimple edition</h2>

<p>Being able to use any container is nice, but sometimes you don&rsquo;t really care and just want to get started. You are covered!</p>

<p>I have created two packages that provide you Silly pre-configured with either <a href="http://php-di.org">PHP-DI</a> or <a href="http://pimple.sensiolabs.org/">Pimple</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li>read more about <a href="http://mnapoli.fr/silly/docs/php-di.html">the PHP-DI edition</a></li>
<li>read more about <a href="http://mnapoli.fr/silly/docs/pimple.html">the Pimple edition</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Those wanting the benefit of autowiring might like the former, while those familiar with Silex might feel more at ease with the latter.</p>

<h2>Beyond Silly</h2>

<p>I hope this example will show how a framework can be built without coupling to a dependency injection container. This was rather easy because it is a micro-framework, but I hope it will give others some ideas.</p>

<p>For those interested to learn more about these topics, everything explained here was actually implemented in a library called <a href="https://github.com/mnapoli/Invoker">Invoker</a>. Feel free to have a look at it and maybe use it in your projects. The same principles shown here could be applied to any framework dispatching to PHP callables. Hopefully it will catch on!</p>

<p><em>Thanks for <a href="https://twitter.com/Darhazer">@Darhazer</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/najidev">@najidev</a> for reviewing this article.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
